And as usual, it takes a minute or two
for it to start up. And I'm going to
admit everyone now.
Good morning everyone. This is Dominic
Zerlo with the New Mexico Department of
Health and this is the dosage
administration and clinical practice
committee meeting. Uh we are admitting
all of the individuals at the moment. So
we'll plea we'll give everybody a moment
or two to get online. In the meantime,
just as the usual reminders, although it
looks like most of the people have been
on previous meetings, but just in case
there's anyone who hasn't, uh we are
recording this meeting. So we do ask
that people keep their language to be
appropriate because we also post this up
online after the meeting is over. And uh
it's also one of the reasons why we do
not have very many people on visual uh
so that we ensure there's nothing uh
untored in the background uh during the
meeting and that we don't have to delete
or bleep things out. Uh the other reason
why we actually keep most of the cameras
off and you'll see me turn mine off
except when I'm speaking is mostly
because uh the bandwidth issue in
various parts of the state. We don't
always have the best bandwidth and video
takes up a lot of that and so we want to
ensure people are not dropping off and
having to rejoin any more than is
absolutely necessary. And so for that
reason we do keep the video off other
than the uh committee chair and a few of
the staff members uh as we join in and
out of the meeting. Anyway, with that
I'll turn it on over to you Ian and uh
the meeting is yours. Well, perfect.
Thank you so much. Good morning,
everyone. Thank you for joining today's
meeting of the dosage administration and
clinical practice committee. Uh my name
is Ian Dunn. I'm the chair of this
committee. I appreciate everyone taking
their time to, you know, participate and
contribute your expertise to this
process. Uh the purpose of today's
meeting and we're going to review as
much as time will permit of preparation
sessions, administration sessions, and
integration session structure within the
medical psilocybin program. Um so before
we begin I want to briefly remind
everyone of the role of this committee.
Committees operate in an advisory
capacity to the medical psilocybin
advisory board. They provide forum for
subject matter experts, stakeholders and
community members who may not serve
directly on the board to share expertise
and help inform program development. The
goal is to expand perspectives,
incorporate professional experience, and
strengthen the recommendations that
ultimately go to the department.
And so before we begin reviewing the
documents, I would like to take a quick
moment for introductions. If you would
like to participate in committee
discussion today, please briefly share
your name, your role or area of
expertise and your interest related to
dosage administration or clinical
practice in the program. Uh if you would
like to participate, go ahead and raise
your hand and I will defer to um the
department for unmuting.
All right, sounds good. It looks like
first up we've got uh Stephanie Duket.
Stephanie, I have allowed your mic. You
can uh unmute yourself when ready. And
uh you do that by clicking the mic icon
that should be up at the top for you.
There you go.
>> Hi. Um, my name is Stephanie Duket and I
own Santa Fe Mountain Mushrooms here in
Santa Fe and I'm just interested in
following this process and becoming a
producer eventually, I hope. All right,
thank you.
>> Awesome. Thank you. And next we have Dr.
Lita Fatimi.
And I have enabled your mic.
Good morning everyone. I'm Dr. Lita
Fitami. I'm an internal medicine
physician and hospice and palative
doctor. Um I also uh aside from my my
medical practice
um we have the conscious physicians
psychedelics academy where we teach
people uh what we're going to talk about
today. So I'm super excited about this
discussion. Thank you so much.
>> Awesome. Thank you. And next we've got
Chris Pesuski. And Chris, you should be
able to talk when ready.
>> Morning everybody. My name is Chris
Puski. I'm a advisory board member. Just
happy to be here and help out. I'm
grateful for all of you that showed up.
>> Awesome. Thanks, Chris. And next we've
got James Brown. James, I have enabled
your mic.
Thank you so much and morning everyone.
Ian, thank you again for being the chair
of this. I do appreciate you and
everybody on this call. My name is James
Brown. I'm a doctor of pharmacy in New
Mexico. I'm a veteran and I just love
what this state's doing and want to
support everybody as well as this state.
I'm representing Five Degrees North
Healing Foundation, a nonprofit that
focuses on veterans, first responders,
patients with trauma, and anything I can
do and be an expertise or anything I
need, just [snorts] let me know. Thank
you.
>> Awesome. Thanks, James. And I don't see
any more hands up right now. Um, again,
to raise your hand if you do want to
speak. Um the raise icon, it's got a
little hand on it, is also at the top
more sort of on the center uh left side
of the top banner there. Um and I see a
couple more hands up. Um next we've got
Shane McDaniel. And Shane, I have
allowed your mic. You can speak when
ready.
Okay, it looks like we might have some
technical difficulties with Shane right
now. It looks like your mic is showing
that it should be um
uh emitting audio, but there's we can't
hear anything on our end. So, you might
want to try to um drop off the call and
then rejoin. And uh hopefully that'll
fix the issue.
Um you can also put introductions in the
chat um for anyone who would like to do
that as well.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. And I did see one other hand up,
but it looks like
>> has been dropped. I didn't catch who
that was. Oh, okay. There. Wh
Okay. Lori Golzar, your hand is going up
and down.
uh several times but let me Lori Golzar
I
have enabled your mic if you wanted to
speak
okay and looks like maybe not um so and
I don't see any other hands up at this
time. So, um I think we Oh, all right.
One more. We've got Gregory Evans.
And Greg, I have enabled your mic.
>> Just got here. Um by the skin of my
teeth. Um Gregory Evans, no affiliation.
Santa Fe,
that is all.
All right, sounds good.
And um if no other hands want to be
raised at this time um I think Ian we
can uh pass back to you.
>> Perfect. Um and Jorge if you wanted to
start sharing the preparation session
structure document
and we can begin reviewing that.
>> Oh and then I guess one more
introduction in the chat and Mets Dr.
Dr. Annmez, clinical facilitator in
Colorado, licensed counselor in New
Mexico, director of Fluence Natural
Medicine Training Program in Colorado,
TA County resident.
>> Perfect. And then we can go ahead and
begin as soon as we get that document.
>> And my apologies. Which one did you want
to do first? The preparation session.
>> Yes.
>> Okay. Thank you. I'll have it up in just
a moment.
>> Perfect. Thank you.
>> Right. And while he's pulling that up,
um Kate Hawk also introduced herself in
the chat. Looks like good morning. This
is Kate Hawk. I'm a psychedelic assisted
therapist with 40 years of trauma
experience. I'm happy to be part of the
New Mexico process.
Okay. And is that showing now?
>> Yes. All righty. So, we will begin
looking at um preparation standards.
These are kind of just a basic outline
of what they need to be. We'll go ahead
and start with purpose. So preparation
sessions establish clinical readiness,
safety planning and informed
participation prior to the
administration of medical psilocybin.
Preparation sessions serve to build
rapport between the facilitator and the
patient to create psychological safety,
trust and openness for therapeutic work.
It helps to identify therapeutic
intentions and goals for administration.
Assess psychological, emotional,
behavioral and medical readiness for
participation. Identify strengths,
vulnerabilities, and support systems
affecting treatment outcomes. Determine
appropriate clinical support to your
placement. Establish clear expectations
regarding program structure, boundaries,
and participation.
Preparation also ensures participants
understand the psychological,
environmental, and experiential aspects
of psilocybin administration. So, going
off of just the purpose, does anyone
have any questions, comments, concerns,
or problems that they would like to
address with that section?
And just as a reminder as well, um
Dominic will be posting um each section
uh that we're going over as we go over
them in the chat uh for us to review.
>> Perfect. All right. So then we can move
on to minimum preparation requirements.
Um a participant must complete at least
one formal preparation session with a
trained facilitator.
Uh, prior to administration, preparation
sessions must occur at least 24 hours
prior to administration. Occur no more
than 60 days prior to administration. I
just followed Colorado on that one. Um,
be conducted by the facilitator who will
be present during administration
whenever possible and be documented in
the participants clinical record prior
to administration. Um, and then
preparation sessions may be conducted in
person or via tele health when
clinically appropriate. So, does anyone
have any questions, comments, concerns,
or problems with this section?
Uh, James
Ian on the my only question on this is
the one at least one. I do like that
wording because it does open up a lot of
um I just didn't know if there need to
be at least two. I just I just want to
make sure that we're doing enough
preparation.
Um, but that's all my thing is. I just
didn't know if the one or we need to
increase that. That's all my thought.
Thank you.
>> Perfect. Thank you. Um
Shane.
Okay. It looks like Shane might still be
having mic issues.
Okay. Ann Mets in the chat says, "Looks
great."
>> Uh, if Shane wants to post it in the
chat, we can go ahead and read it out as
soon as um we finish with the other
hands.
[clears throat]
>> All right. So, next we've got Chris.
Um, I just want to say I think 60 days
prior might be a little long. I I would
like to see that reduced to 30 perhaps.
I I just think that's a a really long
time between preparation and
administration if it were to take that
whole time.
>> Okay. Um, and then I do want to bring up
Shane McDaniel said that is an
integration coach considered a
facilitator? And yes um they would be no
sorry no they are separate
parts of the process. So a facilitator
would be during the administration
session. Um an integration coach could
be after. Could they be the same person?
Sure. But they are different um jobs.
All right. And then
Dan uh Dr. Lita Fatime.
I hope I said that right.
Yes, Fami. Thank you. Um, yeah, I agree
with both James and Shane. And, um, I
would, you know, people tend to go by
the lowest, uh, qualification possible.
Is there a possibility to put a range in
there for people to think because there
are people in the community that need or
have needed in the past like two months
of preparation um two months of trauma
therapy in order to have um a you know a
successful outcome. And in fact in
research when you look um at Hopkins you
know that's the model we use and you see
this you know throughout research um
they do eight weeks or eight sessions of
preparation beforehand and then the
highdose session and then eight sessions
afterwards of spiritual care of trauma
therapy and so one is great you know and
I know there are many people in the
community who many years of experience.
So, I get that. I just think that maybe
giving a range. I don't have a good
answer to it. And you know, you don't
want to require everybody to to have to
go through two months of preparation.
Um, that may be the right thing to do. I
don't know. But I think having a range
maybe at least one to four you know in
the language so that people when this is
released um people don't just don't go
just buy the one and say that's for
everybody you know.
>> Yeah. Um and I've definitely tried to
make this program stabilization
first. So what that means is and why to
kind of answer both questions um why
it's 60 days prior to administration is
if they're taking a medication like
let's say lithium and their their
prescriber and their um psilocybin
recommener also say you know what maybe
we can taper them off and we can get
them done but the intention for the
psilocybin and the preparation for
safety still is done in that first
session with the psilocybin professional
and the tapering down would be done with
their actual doctor that was prescribing
it. And so when those two are working
together, I don't want to say, oh well,
your work that was done to prepare for
the psilocybin, the tapering off and
such is just not worth anything because
we didn't give enough time in the
regulation. I would be okay with saying
more than one formal preparation
session. I have seen that be pretty
common in the research as well. Um the
reason I had kept it at at least one is
because there are going to be you know
many psychiatric conditions as well as
phys uh pathophysiological conditions
are um
they come in ranges. And so if someone
has PTSD and is still experiencing um a
number of symptoms, maybe they don't
need um and they're experiencing a
number of more mild symptoms, maybe they
don't need um as much preparation, but
maybe someone who was, you know, a
veteran and has been to war could need a
little bit more preparation or maybe a
little bit less. I'm not exactly an
expert on veterans, but I did want to
bring up that point. Uh, and then
Dominic was next.
>> Yeah, thank you, Ian. And thank you, uh,
Dr. Fatami. That's actually a great
point and fits in with what I was going
to suggest is rather than making it
specifically one session, maybe what it
needs to be is um, participate in at
least say 3 hours worth of preparation
uh, sessions. That way it could also be,
you know, that would mean that it'd be a
minimum of two or three sessions at
either an hour and a half or an hour
each. And that way, and that could be
spread over time. Um, the one thing to
remember is while ranges are really
good, you know, we could potentially put
this in a range of something like a
minimum of 3 to eight hours, it becomes
a little more difficult when doing that
in a formal setting because, as you
mentioned, Dr. Fatmi most people quite
often are just going to try to go for
the minimum and we want to ensure that
it's actually a medical decision not
something that's actually requ that you
know that people are just going through
steps due to you know the guidelines or
the regulations we want to make sure
they're doing it because it's what's
truly appropriate for the patient and so
to do that but I think it could be
something where if we look at hours
rather than sessions because then it
could potentially be multiple sessions
if that's what the patient needs. Um or
it could be done in a block for example.
Um especially if it's being done under
some of the situations that we know have
occurred and are having. So um you know
if that works out well I think that
might be an alternative to rather than
just saying one session but using hours.
>> I would concur with that. Uh Chris
Um, so I guess I kind of have a question
here. I I scrolled down in the document
just a little bit, but I think it's
relevant to this conversation, too. Are
we including like an initial screening
with med um medical interactions in the
preparation or I I kind of thought that
might be handled in the patient
qualification and safety committee but
but it I I feel like that should almost
be a separate process and then you would
have to rescreen before you even begin
uh a formal preparation for psilocybin
treatment. Um
just thought
Yeah, and I appreciate that. Thank you.
Um,
yeah, we will address that a little bit
later. In my mind, preparation included
many things, including that. Um,
we in in healthcare, we often double
check things. So, it would be checked by
the provider and then checked just again
to make sure, oh, they have the safety
plan in place, they have that kind of
thing. Um,
uh, James,
you know, just going back to that first
line, I mean, I'm good with the other
stuff. I just think, you know, again,
with the past training I've had and
other wording that's out there prior,
like Ann said in the chat, two, I think
we need to say at least two and then you
open up to the hours. But I I think
people with what we're going after with
the ICD10 coding and I think what with
we're going after with those four health
indications.
I think that we need two because some of
those people change. I don't think
you're really going to see the true
person sometimes in one of these maybe
one session is I don't think you're
going to see somebody truly. You can get
faked out. Um you know in in Oregon
where we where we work I think you know
you don't see you just meet with them
for a few minutes. It's kind of crazy
even, you know. Um, but it has to be 24
hours in. I do like that. Um, and I do
like your 60-day because of the lithium
like you're saying, you make some good
points. So, but just I think the wording
on two with the like Dom said and Dr.
Fatimi. Um, I think it's it's a great
idea of giving hours. Thank you.
>> Yeah. Uh, Dom, could you actually just
strike the at least one formal
preparation and do the three hours of
formal preparation instead of one
preparation session?
I'm actually writing a little bit of
language and I'll put that in the chat
in just a moment.
>> Perfect. Thank you.
>> Well, and I can read the last couple
chats real quick. Um, so Kate Hawk says,
"Very clear. I also prefer prep within
30 days. Conditions can change. Ideally,
there will be more than one prep
session, but in the interest of
accessibility, I'd agree to leave that
up to the providers. A range is
realistic, and one to four is
essentially the same as at least one
legally. Um, and of course, some people
will need more preparation. Cost and
availability will affect preparation in
practice.
And then Katherine Sanchez says, "And if
the wording doesn't work, that document
can probably be adjusted at a later
date." And Matt says, "I think that's a
good solution." Dominic, many healing
centers in Colorado require two prep
session. Whoops. Let's see. Okay, where
was I? Oh, okay. Uh, require two preps
as part of the protocol. I think leaving
some room for clinical judgment is
important. And as Kate says, cost
increases with every extra clinical
hour. Uh Leaf Fi says, "I agree to
having an initial session for client
intake to determine eligibility
and no uh contraindications."
And then Shane
[clears throat and snorts] McDaniel,
uh at least two 1-hour sessions is
recommended. Uh the first session is an
introduction and the second session is
where the work actually begins. And then
Dominic posting that language in there.
Um, James Brown responding, "If we use
the ICD coding, we will be able to
potentially bill these sessions."
>> Yes, we can. It is my understanding that
we will be able to bill everything
except for the actual administration of
the
psilocybin. Um,
again,
>> just sorry, Ian, just to be clear, we're
working on it so that we'll be able to
help provide codes to be able to do so,
but we uh and we're meeting with HCA and
Medicaid uh actually in the next week to
discuss some of that. And so, we're
hopeful that we'll be able to find codes
that will work for all of it, but the
actual administration. So, but no
promises yet. We have to have that
discussion.
>> Yes. Um
all right. So with um
so before we jump into other areas, Ian,
what about the language? Does the
language that I put in the chat, does
that sound good to people? A minimum of
two formal preparation sessions of at
least an hour each with a minimum of
three hours total.
>> Yes. So I will open discussion on that.
Does anyone have any objections to
changing the language to minimum of
those two formal preparation sessions of
at least an hour each with a minimum of
3 hours total. So they need more they'll
get more.
Uh Lisa,
>> hello. Thank you um for allowing the
space to speak. Uh my name is Lisa. I'm
a program director of Chunga Institute.
We're accredited in Oregon, Colorado. I
think requiring two preparation session
is going to be um a bit a burden on the
practitioners because most of the
clients as you mentioned before will be
requiring only one official preparation
session and a day of the session and
requiring a second preparation session.
we have to put in the time that needs to
be compensated either by the client or
it will be built at the expense of the
practitioner. And um through our
experience in Oregon, Colorado, we see
that indeed most clients require only
one preparation session um because a lot
of paperwork is administered online
through medical portals. So all that
will be filled up online by
practitioners re uh participants and
practitioner will review it and then
have the proper preparation session. So
I would keep minimum of one session just
to make sure that
either a client is not paying for the
second session or the practitioner is
not doing it for free if it's not
required.
Thank you.
So
I think it is important that we separate
out the two
um
sessions. I think it's more important
that we get a total of number of hours.
That way we can ensure that people are
getting reviewed comprehensively and not
just filling out a form and then signing
off.
because realistically this shouldn't be
an administrative task. It should be a
clinical task and a lot of times
it can just be rushed. So I do think
that the two formal preparation sessions
of at least an hour each is is a pretty
solid foundation. How about you Chris?
>> Um I I think that's good especially if
we're going to keep the clinical
screening portion in there. Although I'm
not sure I agree with redundancy in that
process too much. It um I've been
talking recently with people in Colorado
who are trying to remove redundancy and
extra paperwork out of their process
just because it's they're finding it
overly burdensome and um rising costs
quite a bit. So just something to
consider in there.
Just I want to add the way it works in
Oregon, Colorado. Usually practitioner
will send the paperwork online and
participant will fill up all the
paperwork before the session online on
their own. Then they will send it back
and then practitioner would review the
paperwork. After the review, they set up
a preparation session. That way
practitioner is fully informed on what's
happening and then they able to have in
that preparation session and in most
cases one preparation is more than
enough because also they have the day of
the session when a practitioner before
the administering the dosage they go
over briefly over the paperwork and also
if anything changed. So technically
you'll have two preparation sessions.
All righty. So let's go ahead and just
have a vote. um if you would rather keep
the one formal preparation session
um
versus if you want to do the minimum of
two formal preparation sessions of at
least an hour each with a minimum of 3
hours total. So let's start with the at
least one formal preparation session. If
you are in support of that, raise your
hand.
All right, I'm seeing five hands.
All right, you can put your hands down.
And then if you are in support of the
minimum of two formal preparation
sessions of at least an hour each with a
minimum of three hours total, please
raise your hand.
Six votes for that. So Dominic, will you
please strike the one formal preparation
session and change it to the hours?
Perfect. All righty. And then if there
is no other discussion on the changes in
this um
I will let you put up your hands if
there's any other things you want to
address with the minimum preparation
requirements.
Okay. And we've got uh Lita Tami with
her hand up. Um did you want to make a
comment or was that just um left over
from the vote?
>> Looks like she
>> Thank you.
>> Okay, gotcha.
>> Okay, cool. And then Kate Hawk,
um
I've allowed your mic. Um did you have a
comment?
It might have also
>> just left over from vote.
>> Okay, gotcha.
>> Perfect. Cool.
>> All righty. If you want to scroll down,
Dominic.
So, clinical screening and eligibility.
So, preparation sessions must include
screening to identify contraindications
or risks. Phil facilitators must review
medical history, psychiatric history,
medication interactions, current
psychological functioning. The review
supports determination of clinical
eligibility and clinical support to your
placement. Participants must demonstrate
capacity to provide informed consent
prior to administration.
Any questions, comments, concerns,
problems they would like to address with
that one?
No. Okay, we will move on.
Informed consent. Oh, we just got one.
and minutes.
>> All right, I have just allowed your mic.
>> Sure. Um I don't know, this isn't quite
captured in I mean sort of in
psychiatric history, but um you know,
one thing I've been bumping up with a
lot in Colorado, um are people with
firstderee relatives um who have history
of psych who have um psychotic disorders
or bipolar disorders. And so maybe I
don't know if it's worth mentioning
something about family history in the
review um or if that's
included in psychiatric history.
That is definitely an interesting point.
Um
there is a very strong genetic component
to psychotic disorders. So I I would
understand where you're coming from.
Given that we don't have a spec it's a
polygenic trait and I can't like
specifically point to whether it is
going to affect you or not. I would feel
uncomfortable with just blanket
disqualifying them. But I would be open
to that if that's what the general
consensus is. I wouldn't say necessarily
blanket disqualifying, but as something
that people ask about in part of the
intake and then they have a conversation
about the potential risks and maybe that
requires
I mean and some of this is the patient
safety work. Um you know that that could
be part of tier 2.
>> Yeah, I mean we could definitely screen
for those kinds of things and put it
into that assessment. Um, but I think it
would be
more so like a risk stratification, just
kind of saying, "Hey, you're at a higher
risk for adverse events." Um, versus,
yeah, like a disqualifying. So, I would
go ahead and add it.
Uh, Chris,
yeah. Should we um be screening in some
way for their support network if we are
treating people and then they don't have
the
know the support afterwards to to deal
with challenging
experiences or [snorts]
paradigm shifts. How I feel like that
should be in here somewhere.
Oh, Ian, you're muted.
There's a section on safety and support
planning um later in the document.
There's one other hand up. Uh, two
others. Dr.
>> Yeah, we've got Lita Fatimi and I think
you're mic is enabled,
so you can unmute when ready.
>> Yeah, just talking about the medical
history and psychiatric history. They um
they include family history in both of
those forms. So, a
that's not something extra that you
would need to add. Um, yeah, family
history is important. However,
just so we are all on the same page
about psychiatric um you know, I don't
want to call them disorders because we
see that they're all many of them are
based in trauma and programming and
patterns versus uh inheritance, genetic
inheritance.
Um and so genetically we, you know, you
want to sure be more cautious, but often
times even a brother having bipolar
disorder does not necessarily pan out to
the sister having one, you know, having
that diagnosis. Um and in fact I would
look more deeply into um adverse
childhood events
um more than I would into family history
though you know it's always advised to
look at family history as well so that
you have a better conversation with the
participant. Thank you.
>> And James
>> Ian, just one recommendation on psychiat
psychiatric history. Can is there any
way to change that to mental health
history? I know in the other screening
forums we do use that terminology. Um
and I think you would encompass more
people versus saying psychiatric. I just
don't want to label it psychiatric. I
was just making a recommendation again
for mental health.
Yeah, thank you. That's fine. Dominic,
can you go ahead and change psychiatric
to mental health?
>> Ready. Oh,
>> I also wanted to uh just point out real
quick in the comments there was a couple
comments uh asking if there was a list
of contraindications.
>> Um yes, from the patient safety and
qualification committee has some
recommendations. There hasn't been
specific contraindications adopted by
the board yet.
Um
I can
I believe it's posted on the website. I
don't know if it has gotten posted yet
though.
Anyway, so are we all good with um
the clinical screening and eligibility
now
or does anyone have any more input that
they would like to add?
All right, cool.
All righty. So, for informed consent, um
informed consent must be obtained
through a direct discussion between the
facilitator and the participant. It may
not be satisfied solely by signature on
a written form. Consent discussions must
address risks, benefits, and
uncertainties, potential psychological
effects, possible physical effects,
altered state of consciousness,
potential impairment of decision-making
during administration. Written
disclosures must include facilitator
identity and permit number,
qualifications, and level of training,
participant right to terminate services
at any time. Any
questions, comments, concerns, things we
should add, things we should remove.
Cool. All right. So, for treatment
orientation Oh, James hand just went up.
>> Sorry, Yen. Um, my only my only question
on this was um
>> I like where we're going with the
consent. I just didn't know on the
consent if we need to say anything about
that ADA stuff with limitations.
I just didn't know. I haven't seen where
that goes yet, you know, as as far as
like individual consent. Are they saying
that, you know, let's say let's say they
have a hearing issue or some type of
other impairment, you know, where where
we fitting that in for if does that fit
in the first part or does that anywhere
else does that fit in the consent area?
I just wanted to bring it up before we
missed the opportunity.
>> Yeah. And so what's meant by discussion
may not be a verbal discussion. It's
just to say what's happening isn't just,
you know, I accept the terms and
conditions. It's allowing them the right
to say ask questions and in whatever
form that that comes about. It doesn't
necessarily have to be a verbal
discussion, but as long as they have
that ability to to rectify any
questions, comments, concerns, anything
that they may have to bring up to the
facilitator that might be making them
uncomfortable. Um, that's kind of where
that was coming from. I just wanted to
avoid that you, you know, that when you
download every app, I accept the terms
and conditions and who knows what I've
agreed to, you know,
uh, Chris.
Um, I'm sorry. And I was just I'm going
over my notes. I think we're moving up a
bit quickly and I I just wanted to make
sure that we weren't missing anything in
here that we should include in our
informed consent.
I think it's pretty broad, but it, you
know, covers all the main areas.
>> Uh, Gregory,
>> hey, how's it going? [clears throat]
Um, maybe
it may be something to be handled
elsewhere, but it might be worth putting
a flag on
a scenario where the patient has
consumed the medicine
and is experiencing a difficult
um on-ramp and wants to stop the session
because that's a very real dynamic that
can happen.
Um, but how we put language around
consent
could affect how practitioners can
handle those situations for the client's
benefit.
So, one thing I did
include here was if they have a
potential impairment of decision-m
during administration.
So yes, they have the right to terminate
the services at any time, but they
cannot make that decision
once they are
in that state and because we don't want
them to go out and you know get injured
when we provided them you know a
psychedelic substance. So, it's it is
about their safety, but that's why we
have to make sure informed consent is so
important is because we're saying, "Hey,
once once you're on the on-ramp, you you
kind of have to ride with us for a
minute and then we'll make sure we can
get you as much help as you can." Um,
that was kind of my understanding. I
don't know if you had under a different
viewpoint on it.
mostly just that if that language is
explicit like somewhere in their con
informed consent saying
>> [clears throat]
>> uh this is the point of no return or
something like that. Um yeah, I don't
know. I just didn't know if it was
something that needed to be called out a
little more clearly, but I'm okay with
the way it is personally.
>> And then James
>> Ian, uh just one section. I don't know,
do we need to include supportive touch
here? You know, cuz that is part of the
consent and it's been included in other
pieces in other states, but that's what
they did. Um, you know, that supportive
touch and then and again transportation
plan. I don't know if those need to be
added as sections here underneath that,
you know, potential impairment, you
know, transportation plan and then that
consent to touch because that'll be
important.
Oh, Ian, you're still muted.
>> Second time today. It is a Monday for
sure. Um, so yes, that is under a second
a separate section. It's under
boundaries and p participant
protections, which basically allows the
participants to decide whether physical
touch may occur, what types of touch, if
any, are acceptable, how consent for
touch will be communicated, and that
kind of thing. Um, it's just it's coming
up. You're beating me to the punch a
little bit.
Okay. And we've got a few things in the
chat if you want me to read any of those
as well.
>> Sure.
>> Okay. Cool. Um so yeah, inmets was just
asking about well sort of related um
what about facilitator uh sorry
facilitator right to terminate services
at any time. For example, someone shows
up intoxicated or appears to have manic
symptoms on administration day. Um okay.
And then James's comments that he
addressed. Um, Lita Feti uh says, "May I
volunteer to provide comprehensive
informed consent that includes all the
considerations discussed here uh which
we use to teach our academy students."
And then last, uh, Shane McDaniel, her
previous statement, an integration coach
is not a facilitator. So, are there um
any of these requirements that a coach
could cover either pre- or post
administration as a coach? I have been
specifically trained on both pre and
post care for psychedelic therapy uh
where some licensed therapists have not.
>> All righty. So, is there anything
else on informed consent that we need to
address?
Uh, Ann,
>> I would just ask that the written
disclosure include the thing I said
about the facilitator right to terminate
it. It's just very important and I think
it's good to have that in the paperwork
if someone if we could add that as a
bullet.
>> Uh, yeah,
I believe we should. I am saying like in
the instance of someone showing up like
acutely intoxicated, they would be
disqualified under the safety guidance
that was provided by the patient
qualification and safety commun
committee. But we can definitely add a
um bullet point saying that the
facilitator retains the right to um
>> yeah just thinking of things I haven't
thought of yet that could be reasons you
would want to
>> stop session.
>> Yeah. And I can completely understand
that they're
people are creative and they'll come up
with a way to
[gasps]
make us need new regulations. So, I
appreciate that. Um,
all right. And then outside of that,
all right, we will go to treatment
orientation.
So participants must receive an
orientation to the treatment process
including what medical psilocybin
services involve, the role and scope of
the facilitator, the overall treatment
process before, during, and after
administration. Participants must
discuss their goals, intentions, and
expectations, reasons for seeking
treatment, and realistic expectations
for outcomes.
questions, comments, concerns about the
treatment orientation.
Uh, Ann, just a quick one. Um, I think
it's really important that we outline
the fact that psilocybin has not been
cleared by the FDA as a treatment for
anything at this point. Um, I think
that's just an important legal
statement that needs to happen that, you
know, at this point it's promising, but
until the time it's been sort of proven
as a treatment for X, I think clients,
sorry, patients really need that
information.
>> I would actually agree and think we
should put it under the informed consent
area. Um, because yeah, they definitely
should know. The FDA does not I forget
what the whole statement is, but FDA
does not approve or certify this product
for use and treatment of any condition.
You know the phrase printed on all the
All right. And then I see
and then I see Dr. Fatim.
Yeah. So under set and setting
preparation I see emotional and mental
readiness which is great. I would add um
I would add physical and spiritual
uh to that.
>> Perfect. Will do.
Chris,
>> um yeah, I was wondering, are we going
to come up with a full-on um informed
consent document? because, you know,
like I said, those were pretty broad and
it I think it was
good broad brush strokes, but there's a
lot of stuff that I think probably needs
to be in there. Um, it's a little bit
more detailed.
>> Muted myself.
>> Um, I believe the forms themselves are
going to be created by the department
pursuant to our recommendations. So, um
I personally was not going to create the
entire document. I believe that once we
transmit what we need the documents to
do that they would be um done, but Dom
has uh better insight than I do.
>> Yeah, Ian, you're exactly right. And so,
Chris, that's a really good point. What
will happen is um once the this is
turned into the regulatory part similar
to what we did with propagation we will
have all of that within you know the
details in there and at least an
example. Um it will at that point be up
to the committee to decide is it a
required standardized form which I would
recommend from a burden standpoint of uh
administratively or if it just needs to
include all of the information that's
listed within the regulatory side. I
hope that helped clear that up a little.
All right. And then so we had kind of
been beat to the punch a little bit but
I don't see any more hands up on set and
setting. Um so let's go ahead and review
that section. Preparation must include
discussion of environmental and
psychological factors that may imp that
may influence the experience. Sorry
about that. Topics must include
emotional and mental readiness,
lighting, temperature and physical
comfort, music or sensory elements used
during sessions, privacy and safety of
the administrative location, access to
restrooms or comfort areas, and
participants must understand how the
environment influences the experience
and safety of administration. Um, and
then
Dr. Fatime had asked [clears throat]
that um physiological and spiritual
health. Please correct me if I'm wrong.
physical and spiritual.
>> Cool.
>> To add that to emotional and mental
readiness. So it would be spiritual,
physical, emotional, mental readiness.
All right. And then we had a comment
from Shane.
Okay. Yeah, unfortunately we can't hear
you, Shane. It it is does pop up with
the icon that shows your mic. Um
but yeah, we're still not getting any
sound.
And next is Harvey King.
>> All right, Harvey King, I have enabled
your mic. You should be able to unmute
when ready. Now,
>> I was just wondering in the uh you I'm
just getting into these meetings and
whatnot, but [clears throat] I would I'm
on I understand that in some indigenous
settings there's often um two
facilitators
and if we've talked about the
possibility of there being or what it
looks like to be a volunteer for th for
those settings if someone that makes
someone feel more comfortable and safe
um regardless if it's the patient or the
provider.
So later we will talk about allowing
like a support person um for the
patients. Um if the administrator wanted
more facilitators there they would be
welcome to do so. Um but I don't think
we would have to list it as a
requirement.
>> Okay. Copy.
>> Um
then I see Chris
Yeah, we put that in there as it
spiritual readiness, but I
think the point was to to make sure that
we're not putting people in spiritual
environments that they're not
uh wanting to be in like that the
spiritual setting is appropriate for the
the people.
Um, and and I think that's a a big
component because there's a lot of
religious trauma in
this space. So I I just don't like that
wording necessarily.
All right. And I see uh Lisa Ginsburg's
hand up. Um, Lisa, I have enabled your
mic. you can uh unmute when ready.
>> Um hello. Yes, I have question around
assessing spiritual readiness. Does
someone need to be qualified and
credential in assessing? How would
someone who is not credential in
assessing spiritual readiness would
assess that? Also, we have to be a bit
careful. people, for example, first
responders, veterans might be triggered
by spirituality and we need to be
mindful of that as well.
>> Thank you. And James,
>> hey Ian, under the setting, I know we're
kind of saying the language of
environmental safety. I just didn't know
if that was the terminology we'd wanted
to use, privacy and environmental
safety.
you know, of the administration
location, something like that. Um, and
with, you know, I agree with Dr. Fatimi
and the rest of the group about other
considerations. Again, going back to
that other or additional considerations,
that would be things like the spiritual
and religious accommodations, things
also like do you need an interpreter?
Things like uh service animal, um things
like speech impairment, auditory,
visual, other things that might be
required. Um, just want to bring that up
again. Thank you.
Yeah. And so what I had I guess
envisioned from spiritual readiness is
not necessarily that
someone is is
um
like
that is going to be assessed, but more
so that it serves as part of their
behavioral health and mental health. in
that a lot of the um feelings that we
associate can often be tied to those
factors. And so
some people like to refer to it as
spiritual, some people refer to just say
that's just my brain. Some people say
the universe, some people say whatever.
But it's not about saying okay, you have
a belief system or anything like that.
is just saying you in whatever you see
as
the
source of light then
if you are ready to accept something
that is going to change how you see the
world often times and so um yeah I just
that was my kind of understanding of it
but definitely feel free to correct me
if I'm wrong uh Chris
Yeah, I I'm just really struggling with
this. I don't know how you
assess spiritual readiness, nor that
that is actual actually actually
necessary. I think it's much more
important to make sure that when we are
matching facilitators with
with clients that we're not putting
those clients, they don't end up in a
setting that
it contains religious ideology that that
doesn't sit well with them. And so it's
not a readiness issue, it's a setting
issue. Like this is how I run my
practice. I do smudging. I have crystals
and an altar and all of that stuff.
That's important for people to recognize
before they get to that that space so we
don't cause harm.
>> Okay. and Gregory
>> as an atheist who believes strongly in
the spiritual realm and has walked
deeply down that path. I feel strongly
that
in aligned with what Chris is saying
forcing somebody to engage, acknowledge
or participate in a spiritual or
religious
measure of quality
feels out of line. I think an individual
practice can promote those settings and
include that in their work, but I don't
think from a programmatic perspective,
it's appropriate.
Uh, Dr. Fatim,
>> um, thank you so much for the
conversation. Um I think you know Ian
what I hear you and what I had intended
um in this conversation about
spirituality is not religion at all.
It's about um understanding where the
participant is coming from. It's not
assessing them for something that is
enforced upon them. It's understanding
where they're at. We do this every day
in hospice care and we ask individuals
where and it's all non-denominational
has nothing to do with religion
organized religion and if it's better to
take that language out I'm in full
support of it but I think it's really
important for facilitators and we know
this that
this space of expanded consciousness
it's a very spiritual space and in In
fact, you know, in the Hopkins study for
in 2016 when they looked at 52
participants for end of life or fear of,
you know, their diagnosis with cancer,
um, it was a mystical experience that
changed their fear of death. And so
having that conversation
I think is important where spiritual
beings having a human experience.
Um but that's again you know this is not
about religion. This is not about
organized anything. This is not about a
patriarchal system enforcing anything on
people's ways of life and belief
systems. It's about us being in tune
with the participants needs and if they
need for example to bring
something with them to the ceremony for
for them to anchor themselves to feel
the love of the universe in that moment
because they practice something that
maybe the facilitator doesn't um but to
be open to it I think it's important and
in fact very powerful
you know, one of our um local Sorry, I'm
walking the dogs. Um, one of our local
very well-known uh researchers at the
global setting is Dr. Rick Strossman
and he wrote the book uh DMT
uh the the spirit molecule. And when I
spoke with him, he says, you know, if
you um live a spiritual life, you're
going to have a spiritual experience
with any psychedelic. And I think we all
can agree to that. Um in the medical
model, we stay very much away from
speaking about,
you know, energy and frequency and and
spirituality. in the psychedelic world
we get to and I think it's a privilege
to be able to expand ourselves in that
way um of our of our you know for our
clients and also when they go back into
their daily life you know a lot of
people do have
practices in the community they may be
Buddhist they may go to a Zen center
they may be Christian Muslim Muslim,
Jew, Jewish, whatever they are, that is
also part of their community support. So
that's just the, you know, meeting
people where they're at and not trying
to veer them in our direction. But if
you all decide that that language is
does not belong, I'm totally behind it.
>> Thank you. I completely concur with your
view. Um, Dominic,
>> good morning again everybody. So, I want
to bring this up because to me this is
about the set and setting preparation.
And so, it's just about that the topics
need to include it. And so, Chris, you
had mentioned earlier and Greg, you had
kind of echoed it a little bit about
ensuring that, you know, that the the
practitioners and the patients are
aligned. And I think that's actually a
part of that conversation. so that we
ensure that the the patients are
actually in alignment with whatever may
be occurring during that administration
day. And so that to me it's not about
saying
you know a practitioner saying this is
the spiritual path we're following but
saying these are some of the spiritual
elements that we include in our
administration day. We want to ensure
that you're okay with them. And so to me
it really sounds as though that should
be brought up, but maybe instead of it
being in the set and setting that that
be done as part of uh the um uh of the
informed consent that that would
potentially be something where the
practitioner would add that in saying
these sessions are utilizing this
particular spiritual um you know uh
millu. And so maybe having something
like that in there uh rather than here
in the set and setting because that was
a part of just what I was sort of
getting from that um as far as from my
understanding with including that in in
any case just as another potential
option because we do want to make sure
that patients and facilitators are
aligned.
>> Thank you. and Lisa.
>> Um, thank you. And I would love to agree
with Dominic and what he just said.
Probably would use and I think in
general we have to be really careful
with the language. I know that Dr.
Fatima called U Sabin session a
ceremony. This is not a ceremony. What
you guys creating in New Mexico is a
medical model. So we need to be careful
with the language. And um what Dominic
said, I think alignment is really
important. However, spirituality is a
separate study, their PhD programs on
spirituality and we need to be careful
for someone who's coming from not
spiritual background a general
psychiatrist might not know and
understand what spirituality mean. And
right now we have deep discussion on
just one word which created a lot of
confusion. people start connecting that
to religion. So I think to avoid that
confusion for people who are not
spiritually attuned to the plant
medicine but will be working with this
we need to really think about the
language we use and probably use an
alignment in general rather than
spirituality
which I am pro- spirituality but I think
for this context we have to be careful
we're not creating indigenous model
we're not creating a ceremony we're
creating a medical model.
>> I agree. So I think the majority of us
are in consensus that let's at least
strike the word spiritual from set and
setting. Um,
and
we will worry.
I believe the informed consent already
has a lot of stuff on.
Let's see.
And then we can also add um
so discuss consent discussion should
include like alignment or
Perfect.
All righty. And then any other things on
set and setting?
I think there was one other thing that
um Shane had put in the chat for oh uh
oh he was asking about um uh what about
video recording sessions and how to
handle that organ allows videotaping but
the video can only be watched at the
location.
So just as a as a note because this is a
medical model that would fall under the
same um medical records type situation.
So it's not really something that's
necessary to include within regulations,
but it is something that could go within
guidelines with regard to that. And just
while I'm while I'm talking, Shane, just
to let you know, yes, we have reached
out to Dr. Straman and he's actually
been uh invited uh to attend these
meetings as well.
All right. And then Chris,
so um I like how you guys handled the
the spiritual component, but I I think
one of my big issues with that
bullet to begin with was the readiness
part. Like are we assessing readiness in
in this or are we orienting people to
their and setting?
Both. We do have to assess that they are
not intoxicated, that they are not um
and that they are physically and
mentally
able to receive this. Um,
we don't want to
get someone, and it doesn't have to be a
complex assessment, but like they're
having a stroke, maybe we should call
911 instead of
moving on with the preparation session
is kind of what we're getting at. Um,
>> yeah. But
>> all right, I'll let her go.
>> And then Gregory.
>> Uh, just to finalize this horse. Um, I
like the way the l I like the
adjustments with that. I wanted to make
it super clear that I am not in any way
opposed to spirituality or ritual. I
think ritual and spirituality play a
huge role in the entirety of this
ecosystem. In fact, I would like to see
a model where
uh I go to the psychiatrist, I go to
whoever is going to say, "Yes, you can
do this thing. I'm going to give you a
list of providers." And some of those
providers are shamans. Some of those
providers are psycho analysts. Some of
those are coaches and people that fit
into the qualification of somebody who
can take you from the prescriber, walk
you into the ceremony, perform that
ceremony, and it's like an entire team.
And if I'm looking for something deeply
spiritual, I can select that from the
market of people and that way the doctor
is not involved in my spirituality
because I've had some very serious
problems with that in the past. And uh
yeah, I'm sensitive, but I'm also very
spiritual, but I'm also an atheist. So,
I don't want somebody mixing up
[clears throat] my space. [snorts] I
like I don't want lot there's a lot of
people I don't want in the room, and my
doctor probably is one of those.
>> Understandable.
>> Anyways, um I appreciate the adjustments
here.
>> Thank you. I appreciate your comments.
Raymond.
>> Hey guys. I don't I don't always um pipe
in too much here, but in some of the
research that I was reading, uh John's
Hopkins refers to self-trcendent
at times, and it describes experiences
that um they move beyond their ordinary
self focus without invoking religion.
So, when we're doing an assessment, are
they self-trcendent?
um they're reporting self-trcendent
states during the session. Um it's not
uh invoking any religion. It's not uh
trampling on that at all, but it is a a
definition that we could use in a
medical model that wouldn't trample on
anyone's feelings or emotions. So that
was just like I said, I don't pipe in
too often, but that was something I saw.
>> Perfect. Thank you.
All righty.
If that is the last comment on set and
setting, we can go on to safety and
support planning. Oh, sorry, Raymond.
No, he put his hand back down. Um, all
right. So, participants and facilitators
must collaboratively develop a safety
plan that includes emergency procedures,
movement within authorized facility
space, fire and environmental safety
procedures, emergency medical services
access. Participants must also develop a
transportation plan ensuring the
participant will not operate a motor
vehicle for 24 hours following
administration. Identific
identification of support persons if
needed and planning for post session
support needs. Questions, comments or
concerns.
Uh, Gregory,
>> 24 hours.
That was Yeah, I mean, if you're gonna
if you're gonna
put a hard line on it like that, um,
[clears throat]
the at least let people take an Uber
home cuz like
I've been trying to get eye surgery and
I don't have a ride home. Um, and this
kind of thing in the medical safety
realm has really impacted my health over
time. So,
um, I don't know. I think 24 hours is a
a bit harsh.
>> Thank you.
Any other comments, questions? Oh,
Chris.
Yeah, Ian, is this where we're saying
we're assessing whether the clients have
the support network required to engage
in psilocybin services?
>> No. Um,
>> is that going to be some somewhere else
in the document? I don't see it anywhere
else.
Um
yes this would be it. It's just the
identification of support persons if
needed. Sorry I had mis understood.
Um,
so I I'm kind of feeling like
like this process should almost be
broken up into two things like an
assessment portion and a preparation
portion because we're we're mixing
things into the two that ought ought to
be separated. Like it if a person is
identifying as not having you know the
the the support necessary to
um to deal with some challenging
experiences. you know, if they arise um
or they get mentally destabilized,
then we shouldn't make it this far into
the process.
So, what's the alternative to
what if someone doesn't have
like uh Greg said, if he didn't have
someone that could drive him,
who knows if they have a support person,
we need to identify them if they exist
and help to bring them in if something
goes wrong.
But realistically,
I can't guarantee that in everyone's
life.
Um,
but James
Ian, my only thought would be adding a
section at the very end here, planning
for post session integration needs. I
think we have to specifically say that
here because we're saying support
support, but we're not saying
integration. So I think that word needs
to be added in there. Thank you.
>> Okay. Um
Okay. So we can add um
an integration.
Let me see if it would go best here
or
I yeah we could put it there. I think I
would rather put it with the treatment
orientation as like integration goals.
Um establish it right then. Um,
but would that work or did you want
something else?
>> That would work. Yeah, that that's fine.
>> Okay, cool. Um, yeah. So, if we can go
ahead and add um
to
the treatment
orientation. So participants must in
their goals, intentions and expectations
add another bullet that they must um
plan.
They must set up an integration plan. um
that way we know they have somewhere to
go after their session. Um to get
support if they need it or um also to
just genuinely process the experience
and to get them the best. So yeah, I
would concur with that. Um Lisa
Okay, looks like she dropped her hand.
>> Oh, I'm sorry. I I was talking I forgot
to unmute my mic. Um, I said I wanted to
second on what James uh just mentioned
on integration. I think it's a important
part and needs to be emphasized not only
integration with the practitioner but
also self integration post session at
home. Um it's very important a lot of
people feel really disoriented after the
session. Um and I really like the 24hour
um
vehicle uh enforcement not use the
vehicle driving which is also important.
A lot of people feel like it's okay for
them to drive and we see people driving
all the time after the sessions. Um,
however, that adds extra stress for
especially for people who are not
experienced and lead to adverse
reactions weeks after the session. So, I
like the 24-hour requirement.
Thank you.
>> All right. And an
I actually am going to say the opposite
about the 24-hour requirement. Um I live
and work in Tus County where there is
not Uber or really a taxi service that's
reliable and um maybe if there would be
a way that we could do 12 hours after
your sort of released from the session
to not drive because you know assuming
people need to come back for integration
the next day if we're doing integration
in person. Um, I think that's just very
important and I think this becomes an
issue of accessibility that what's
realistic and feasible in, you know,
Albuquerque,
um, Cruises or Santa Fe is not realistic
in some of the other communities where
people are going to be served. Um, and
so I would just ask that that be 12
hours after VA session is has completed.
My only problem with that is that
you know alone
solicit has um uh
elimination halfife of 2 to four 2 to
five I believe hours. Um what that means
is that after 12 hours after the
administration,
there's still about um
half to a quarter left in of the dose
left in your body. And
given that it has such noticeable
effects on um motor coordination, that
is a concern to me. I do recognize that
there's not a lot of um
>> Could you do it 24 hours after the
taking of the administration rather than
saying like at the end of the
administration? So like you take it at
9:00 a.m. 9:00 a.m. the next morning you
can drive again. I mean, I just to not
be able to drive at all the very next
day is really an unfair burden to place
on people living in rural communities
and I think will be an issue for the
accessibility committee.
>> Yeah, I recognize that. But I
also recognize that
psilocybin on its own can have a huge
half-life. And if I would think the
towist drivers would much rather us
limit them to not driving as much the
next day to
than to be hit by a a driver on
psychedelics because we didn't give it
time to wear off.
I think that's a very scary thing if
we're now instead of working within how
long the drug takes to wear off, we're
working with how long it's convenient
for people.
That would be a huge problem.
>> I don't think it's about convenient. I
think it's about this is an issue of
equity and that that's a realistic
requirement in communities where there
are are alternatives.
Okay. Well, thank you. Um, Lisa,
um, thank you. I I just I think we
should put the safety of clients first
and I personally think it's unsafe and
also unwise to let people drive after
the session for the next 24 hours.
Psilocybin is quite
strong
medicine that affects the brain and can
lead to very very deep
reactions in the system and cause long
psychosis that can last anywhere from 4
months to years and be untreated. And we
should think about that and make sure
that we prevent adverse reactions in
clients especially that can last for
such a long time.
>> And Shane,
sorry, we're still not getting any
audio. Uh, Shane.
>> All right. And then since the
transportation plan is a divisive issue,
um, what I'm going to go ahead and do is
we'll have a vote on the duration of
time. So,
if you want it to be 12 hours
versus if you want it to be 24 hours.
Um, so at this time if I could, if you
want it to be 24 hours, please raise
your hand.
Thank you. Please put your hands down.
All righty. And then if you want it to
be 12 hours, please raise your hand.
All righty. With six votes for 24 hours
and 12 votes for or four votes for 12
hours, um we have adopted the 24-hour
waiting rule um
for the safety. Outside of that, um
transportation plan, is there any other
comments, questions, or concerns on this
section?
Cool. Then we will go ahead and scroll
down to boundaries and participant
protections.
So preparation must preparation must
establish clear expectations regarding
boundaries during um administration.
Participants must be informed of whether
physical touch may occur. What types of
touch, if any, are acceptable? How
consent for touch will be communicated?
How boundaries will be protected during
alter states of consciousness.
Participants must also be informed if
any of the following may occur. The
presence of a co-f facilitator, the
presence of additional support persons,
audio or video recording of the session.
All right, I will now allow any hands
for discussion on the boundaries and
participant protections. Uh Chris,
>> so it seems to me that the participant
should be driving the conversation
rather than be informed of
um and I guess that kind of depends on
what kind of touch is allowed or or
whatnot. And you know, I think Colorado
is a little bit more restrictive, but
um they they should be in the driver's
seat on this as far as I'm concerned.
>> You are absolutely right. That is a
typo. I believe that's supposed to be
facilitators
must be informed. But yeah, I do agree.
It's the participants decision. I may
have just worded it wrong on what is
acceptable to them versus what um
must um instead of that. Yeah, I
completely agree. Sorry about that. Uh
James
Um, you know, to Chris's point, I think
that's where we're missing the
facilitator piece of it. Consent we call
it. Thank you. And then the other thing
was just me. Again, I think, you know,
to be on the safe side, we limit touch
to three touches. Head, hands, and feet.
And there's a lot of stuff out there
about adverse outcomes. Bad things
happen sometimes. And we got to be
realize that and say, you know, I think
we need to restrict the three touch to
again heads, hands, and feet. But that's
just me. Thank you.
>> Cool. And
I would concur with that, Chris.
>> Yeah. I'm wondering are we having that
discussion now or is that going to be
dealt with in administration because is
this is prep right?
>> Yeah. So yeah so this is just about
establishing the boundaries um for
administration. If we want we could
strike the entire section and put it in
just the administration.
Uh, I think it's important to have the
conversation in prep and develop a touch
touch contract. Um, but I just wasn't
sure if you wanted to go into what types
of touch we should deem acceptable.
I honestly
feel as though it's the whole consent
thing. I mean, right, it all depends on
what traumas or things we've experienced
because to someone being touched on the
head might not be okay. Um,
but yeah, uh, Dr. Fatim.
>> Um I would have to agree you know the so
I I like the the limits uh for sure in
our consent form that we use in our
academy we teach from as well. Um we
also have a field for consent uh for
body work um and people can click that
and they get consented during the
session. Um
and they you know I I do believe that
this should be part of intake so that as
you and consent as you guys were
mentioning so agree with that you know
there are a lot of body workers in our
community I I'm a doctor of osteopathy
trained um also in uh MD training at UNM
but I do see a huge need sometimes in
session for individuals to um even if
it's you know it's their feet or some
people use acupressure points to relieve
a particular stuckness that might be
happening. So
yeah, the language there I wouldn't I
don't know. I'm I'm a big fan of
guidance without complete restriction
and to allow people to have agency um
within safety guidelines of course
because yes there's a shadow side of
psychedelics we all know about um that
we're trying to um guide ourselves out
of um and but I think it's a it's a
conversation to be had you know may
maybe the language is just you know head
um hands and feet maybe that's you know
that's what the committee decides but I
think there can be a lot of therapeutic
benefit if there is more somatic work
especially when it's you know uh you're
trying to land the individual towards
the end of the sixth hour this just a
conversation I'm not trying to change
anything necessarily here
>> yeah and I really appreciate that I
think I am with you I don't I am not a
big fan of like putting making um
doctors into like robots telling them
exactly what to do. But I do believe in
clinical guidance and to say here here's
what we would you know do
make it your own fit it into your
practice but here's kind of the general
philosophy and yeah I just really
appreciate your comment. Uh, James,
>> thanks Ian. Um, one thing too is
personal bias. I don't see we haven't
talked anything about facilitator
personal bias. That comes up a lot. And
again, I think going back to the
literature, there's a lot of literature
that points to not necessarily good
outcomes, bad outcomes when
practitioners, not outside natural
medicine
ethics, um, have applied this in the
past. So we got to be careful. And so I
think that we need to very be very
careful about touch because it's
something that I think that people need
what I call other holistic treatments
and remedies and that might go into
there right where you're doing raiki
therapy you're doing yoga you're doing
other things and those boundaries might
go into there of like whether it's not
physical touch but other treatment
modalities or other natural treatment
remedies used just a thought to throw it
in there you know cuz they should be
informed Hey, I could use music and all
that stuff, but also raiki and kind of
does say some of that, but I just didn't
know if we wanted to kind of language it
that way for other modalities or we've
kind of discussed it before. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
And then I see uh James Feria.
>> All right, J.
>> Yeah, thank you. Uh yeah, I was just
wanted to add on that as well as you
know when we if we specify something so
specific like heads, hands and feet,
there's you know what if somebody wants
you know needs the their shoulder
touched well, you know, and that's their
way of doing I really think this is up
to the patient and their provider as far
as the specifics. If we wanted to do
something to prevent outrageous things
like sexual contact or something like
that, that seems like something that'd
be appropriate to put in here. that it
it really feels like this is some a
conversation that the provider and the
patient should have.
>> Thank you. Uh Lisa,
>> yes, I think I I would like to agree
with everyone um on the use of touch
with the prior consent. Um and I believe
the consent should be set up the day uh
I mean during the preparation session
and then reviewed on the day of the
session and that should not be changed.
If someone opted out from touch and said
I don't want any touch during the
preparation and they confirmed that on
the day of the session and then during
the session itself they decide to want
to have touch I think that should not be
allowed and you should stick with the
consent that was set in place during the
preparation and the day of the session
before the session. uh but allowing
various touch like shoulder touch is
seems to me logical especially with the
proper training on administering touch
and consent. Um so want to add that.
Thank you.
>> Perfect. Thank you and Chris.
>> Yeah. Uh I think one part we're missing
in here too might be that facilitators
and clinicians might have boundaries as
well like you know not touching your
feet. Um and I don't know if we need to
put that in into this um but it seems
relevant.
Uh yeah and then Dr.
Thank you. And you know, I'm going to go
back to the touch comment that came up.
Lisa, thank you for your comment. And I
would say that during sessions,
sometimes situations come up where you
have to touch. You know, I have I've had
uh sessions with physicians who were
holding on to so much trauma and they
were purging it through dry heaving for
an hour and a half. and it required me
to touch even if in the consent form it
said that you know I don't want to be
touched which you know that almost never
happened but um in this case I had to I
was holding her head back for an hour
and a half while she was dry heaving and
so I think um that's part of the care in
psychedelics psychedelic care it's the
service that we provide and in fact if
you look at Stan Grath's B and John
Halifax who's also local here. Um they
issued very high doses of LSD at the end
of life and one of the main things they
talk about and Joan talks about to this
day is that they sat held hands and
we're were there in a very caring way
for their clients. And so the care to me
is if in session someone is needing
something that we need to be there for
again of course with you know putting
away like making sure that we're all on
the same page that there should be no
sexual contact uh whatsoever. That is
absolutely yes. But as for the
psychological safety and nervous system
regulation and safety of the individual
as they're you know going through the
journey I think it's very important for
us to um have maybe have that
conversation with individuals as well
that you know that piece of paper does
not
negate the fact that we're humans
treating humans.
Thank you.
Doc or Lisa Ginsburg.
>> Um, thank you. So, I'd like to agree
with what just uh Dr. Fatima said. Um, I
think there should be a separation of
the touch. Um I think consent is
important especially when working with
physical or sexual abuse victims. Uh we
want to honor the desire for autonomy
and
during the session sometimes especially
not um seasoned practitioners might feel
an urge to offer supportive touch and if
someone opted out from the beginning and
said I don't want any touch. I'm working
through my own trauma. We have to honor
that. So now what Dr. for Tima said
during the adverse reactions when
someone's purging when someone if we're
working with older populations and they
have mobility issues and need to assist
them to the bathroom hold their hands
that of course no doubt should be
allowed um under specific circumstances
and I think that should be also
specified in this um in this boundary
protocol
Perfect.
Thank you.
Uh, Gregory Evans,
[clears throat]
are we concerned about um
restraint in situations that require um
protocol outside of like our plan?
like if somebody becomes a danger to
themselves or others,
hopefully we don't get there with all
the planning that we do, but
>> um
>> if someone were I think that would be
911, but Dominic,
>> it would fall under the emergency
protocols. So, uh that would be a part
of that planning in that unusual
instance.
Perfect.
And then James,
>> Ian, going back to what the group's kind
of saying with the supportive touch
definition. Um, I think we definitely
need to include something here about,
you know, facilitator u may always
utilize touch to protect a part a
patient's body from immediate or
imminent harm. you know, something like
that was a disclaimer,
you know, but I think that might, you
know, I don't know if it fits again like
you guys are saying here or there, but I
think that needs to go in there. And
again, that'd be like Dr. Fatima said,
taking them uh vital signs if we need
vital signs. Um, restroom fall, right?
Let's say they're walking around and
they might fall or hazard themselves,
you want to jump in there. Um, or other
life-saving procedures. Just a thought.
Thank you.
Yeah, I would um
I would authorize that in an emergency
supportive touch may be used um or in
the case of severe adverse reactions.
Um
that would be within our realm. I would
support that.
All right. And then is there any other
outside of the supportive touch which
has been added as an asterisk? Um does
anyone
have anything else they would like to
say on this issue?
Gregory, did you want to speak again or
was that a remnant hand?
All right. And James, did you have
anything to say?
All right. Now we will go to group
preparation. Um
if administration
>> I'm sorry I'm sorry to interrupt Ian. It
just um from the department of health
we're going to have another meeting that
starts right at 11:00. So I just want to
make sure that we're able the staff are
able to jump over to that meeting. Um so
my apologies. Um if we think we can get
through group preparation in the next
five or six minutes um I think that's
great. If not, I would just say we need
about five minutes for us to uh get over
to the other meeting. So, I just wanted
to do a time check there.
>> Will you just um notate in the document
where we stopped and then we can resume
this at another time?
>> Absolutely. And I do have an answer for
um uh I think it is Kate
uh had a question in the chat just about
the driving safety and uh that had been
changed to after administration.
Yes, it's I meant 24 hours from the
second the
whatever the homogenized mushroom
touches your tongue. That is when we are
starting the timer. It's not waiting
until we've done everything and you've
gone through and then another 24. Um
all righty. Well, um we need to set a
meeting.
So, we are going to go ahead and pause
the document where we are at. [sighs]
How does
Monday the 30th sound to everyone?
All right. Monday the 30th at 9. I'm
seeing a lot of thumbs up.
>> Yeah. And that's good for us. Cool.
Cool.
All righty, guys. Well, thank you so
much for showing up and having
discussions with me. Um, I really
appreciate everyone taking the time to,
you know, just be here today and to help
out with the development of our program.
Uh,
yeah, that's pretty much all I have to
say until we meet again on the 30th. I
wish you guys a wonderful rest of your
week. Be safe everyone.
>> Thank you on behalf of the department to
Ian for chairing this and to everyone
else for participating. Hope you all
also have a very great week.